<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loyal remembrancer: or, A poem dedicated to the queens most Excellent Majesty, and may serve as a remembrance to all posterity.</title>
            <author>Crown, S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7372A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1048_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867111</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867111</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81083)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1048[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loyal remembrancer: or, A poem dedicated to the queens most Excellent Majesty, and may serve as a remembrance to all posterity.</title>
                  <author>Crown, S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R. Wood, 1650. But not permitted to be publick till now,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dediction signed: S. C., i.e. S. Crown.</note>
                  <note>Mostly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novem 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English poetry --  Early modern, 1500-1700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Loyal Remembrancer: OR, A POEM DEDICATED To the Queens moſt Excellent Majeſty, And may ſerve as a Remembrance to all Poſterity.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Queenie</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>R. Wood,</hi> 1650. But not permitted to be publick till now, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168981:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168981:2"/>
            <head>To the Royal Majeſty OF Henrietta Maria, Queen of Great Brittain, France, and Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is now high time that your Princely eyes ſhould no longer contract Redneſs from Tears, but a brave fire from revenge, that you ſhould deal with your paſſion as the generous <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> with that infamous fire-brand of the World, that Canker to the Royal tock and Branches, <hi>Cromwel,</hi> ſuffer it to poſſeſs ſome Out-skirts and Frontiers of your Soul, that by the expanſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his incroachments, its ſpirits may be waſted and laid open for ruine; And your victorious reaſon (contracting all its forces) ſweep all ſuch Treacher us invaders from the face of the World, and leave nothing of it in Nature but a memory, which may make it ſtink to all Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Porcia</hi>'s Coals are of no further uſe for deſpair, all they can be ſerviceable in, is to create a flame to which the Barbarous rebels muſt be fuel, and the fire may be a purifier to the region of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, cleering all the air from thoſe two greateſt plagues to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and mankind, <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Regicide:</hi> God has now ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them for the Sickle of <hi>Revenge;</hi> it is highly opportune to ſhake them from the Trees of Authority and Rapine where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n they hang: And ſince hanging is natural for ſuch <hi>Gomorrah Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Tyburn</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is the propereſt place in the World for ſuch Fruits, if their rottenneſs be not too violent Eye ſores to the view, and of too great a ſtench to the Noſethrils of Paſſengers.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:168981:3"/>
            <p>The <hi>30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>January</hi> ſhall be reckoned amongſt thoſe Ominous dayes which are fatal to the repoſe and ſafety of Nations, which though it antecede here that in <hi>England</hi> by ten dayes, yet my paſſion of <hi>Revenge,</hi> and my engagement to follow that Standard of your Heroick Son, which muſt cary with it a reſtitution of the World to Laws, Liberty, Religion, Conſcience, and all other O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns Divine and Humane, hath made me make uſe of the Kalender in <hi>France,</hi> and preſent an <hi>Anniverſary</hi> upon the moſt horrid Murder the Sun ever viewed; not to ſtir up your un ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampled piety to tears, but to awake your own royal and other loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Boſomes to revenge; which when it ſhall break forth in its juſt magnitude and dimenſions, the <hi>Rebells</hi> will then confeſs, <hi>That Our ſilence is like a Calm, whoſe unſuſpected Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility is followed by nothing leſs dangerous then totally ſubverting Earth-quakes, or univerſal conſuming Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> The <hi>Perſian Princes</hi> had a conſtant Moniter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them of <hi>Greek</hi> affronts and injuries, may this <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary</hi> be your <hi>Remembrancer</hi> that all <hi>Europe</hi> is engaged to your aſſiſtance; That you have a Fate more noble im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nding then to live in Exile, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-revenged; That you have a SON, who by his fiery perſecutions and vertues, will one day make good in his examples all which is related of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt excellent Princes; That there is a Nation which with infinite groans im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plores its reſtitution to Monarchy, its redemption from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> in whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h it is fatally captivated and engulphed and (which <hi>Madam</hi> deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves a lower rank amongſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe more Majeſtick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let it be a ſpeaking teſtimony to the World, that I am (in ſpight of all the revolutions occaſioned by Thieves, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, and Regic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties and all your Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies moſt humble and never changeable Servant and Subject, <hi>S. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168981:3"/>
            <head>Allegiance to the memory of our late Murthered Soveraign.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SUch was the Pride of Murther in our loſs,</l>
               <l>To dub the Scaffold equal to the Croſs:</l>
               <l>Since the Worlds Crucifix all Butcheries</l>
               <l>The Jury finds Chance-medly unto this.</l>
               <l>The Primitive and Modern Martyrs all,</l>
               <l>Members of <hi>Charles</hi> his Body myſtical,</l>
               <l>The Univerſal Bill of Martyrdom,</l>
               <l>In him contracted to a total ſum.</l>
               <l>'Tis thought thy Saviour, onely Prieſt, would dye,</l>
               <l>And leave his Kingly ſufferings to thee.</l>
               <l>In life and death his Vice-Roy as if all</l>
               <l>His Offices were Hypoſtatical.</l>
               <l>How durſt they think he mortal was, or ſay</l>
               <l>He leſs then Angels were aſſumed Clay?</l>
               <l>Fool'd Tyrant Wretches who believe him dead,</l>
               <l>Who from <hi>Humanitie</hi> but vaniſhed.</l>
               <l>Faith being weak, a Demonſtration's He,</l>
               <l>To looſe the Riddle of <hi>Theanthrophie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To all religious under ſtanding Eyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Humanitie</hi> was but his late Diſguiſe.</l>
               <l>But ſo much Deity may juſtly grudge,</l>
               <l>To be condemn'd, and <hi>Barrabas</hi> his Judge.</l>
               <l>When every drop of bloud he ſhed, was much</l>
               <l>Too precious to redeem the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouls of ſuch,</l>
               <l>For had old <hi>Adam</hi> ſpawn'd no better ſeed,</l>
               <l>Th'Eternal Son had never liv'd or dy'd.</l>
               <l>If his Poſterity had all been ſuch,</l>
               <l>The Bloud of Bulls and Goats had been too much.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:168981:4"/>
               <l>Lord, was it not enough, thy ſelf to dye,</l>
               <l>But thou muſt ſuffer too by <hi>Deputie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who his pure Breath a prey to Villains gave,</l>
               <l>Not worthy to be Sextons to his Grave.</l>
               <l>Shov'ling his Monarchie, as if it muſt</l>
               <l>Follow like Earth to Earth, and Duſt to Duſt.</l>
               <l>How will the <hi>Hoogen</hi> Chandlers ſcorn our fate,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Hewſon</hi> vampes and underlayes the State?</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pride</hi> in Ale, and Dray-man <hi>Buffe</hi> ſhall ſing</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'ve ſlain <hi>Goliah</hi> with a Small-Beer Sling.</l>
               <l>And drawn our Royalty ſo near the Lee,</l>
               <l>This hand muſt tappe a well-hop'd Anarchie.</l>
               <l>'Tis time to paſs from this infernal hoſt,</l>
               <l>From whom I riſe as from the Nethermoſt:</l>
               <l>And paſs, as through a Purgatorie flame,</l>
               <l>To a prepared Bliſſe in <hi>Charles</hi> his Name.</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt I with trembling and Religious care,</l>
               <l>Do go unto my mourning as my Pray'r.</l>
               <l>I do repent I have prophan'd his Herſe,</l>
               <l>And ſacred Aſhes with un-hallow'd Verſe.</l>
               <l>To whom, as one Religious Votarie,</l>
               <l>Three Pilgrim Kingdoms owe their Pietie.</l>
               <l>Though Saint's too mean a Name for him, we know</l>
               <l>His Vertues Canoniz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d him here below:</l>
               <l>God did to him ſo much his Likeneſs deal,</l>
               <l>'Tmight ſeem his ſecond Precept to repeal.</l>
               <l>He appears not onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tir to every ſence,</l>
               <l>But Spheare; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e his own Intelligence:</l>
               <l>So glorious that this Riddle he begets,</l>
               <l>The Sun then ſolely riſes when he ſets.</l>
               <l>Whoſe Guide his ſaving light is ere they reſt,</l>
               <l>Shall over take the Wiſe men of the Eaſt.</l>
               <l>Who ſo his wiſdoms juſt Admirer is,</l>
               <l>Says <hi>Solomon's,</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ypical to his.</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168981:4"/>
               <l>Had they, and <hi>Shebahs</hi> Queen liv'd at one time,</l>
               <l>With what delight would ſhe have honour'd him!</l>
               <l>For why his Continence was ſo Divine,</l>
               <l>He it alone embrac'd as Concubine.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Veſtal</hi> might have lain with him in bed,</l>
               <l>And riſe with her Religious Maiden head.</l>
               <l>How did he in St. <hi>Michaels</hi> Angel-vein</l>
               <l>Confute thoſe evils which durſt him arraign!</l>
               <l>If we the Maſter-roll of Virtues call,</l>
               <l>The name of <hi>Charles</hi> may anſwer for them all.</l>
               <l>As what we attribute to God muſt be</l>
               <l>It ſelf, the abſolute Divinitie.</l>
               <l>So reaſon coupled with moralitie,</l>
               <l>This Definition gets that they were he.</l>
               <l>Who now for either ſeeks (he being ſpent)</l>
               <l>Without a Subſtance looks for Accident.</l>
               <l>But, as the Sun ſets onely unto Us,</l>
               <l>And never ſhines himſelf leſs glorious.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Sols</hi> eclipſe was to improve his Light,</l>
               <l>But ſmother us in an Egyptian Night.</l>
               <l>As Earth-quakes do deſtroy from mile to mile,</l>
               <l>And faſt Foundations ſilip Croſs and Bile,</l>
               <l>The Center yet being never ſtirr'd at all;</l>
               <l>So we (not <hi>Charles</hi>) are bruiſed in his Fall.</l>
               <l>His execution was his Subjects Pain,</l>
               <l>They loſt their King, and yet their King doth raign,</l>
               <l>Not as a Deaths-head ſhell, or a Grave-ſtone,</l>
               <l>Memento's are for Mortals of their own.</l>
               <l>In this ſad Paper every one may ſee,</l>
               <l>His Epitaph, in his own Elegie.</l>
               <l>Without a Contradiction 't may be ſaid,</l>
               <l>Though he did Dye, not he, but we are Dead.</l>
               <l>What dying life is ours, that He muſt dye,</l>
               <l>And we, that do ſurvive him, Putrifie?</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168981:5"/>
               <l>But ſtay, his Urne is warm; and, at his Name,</l>
               <l>His Aſhes ſtart, and wake into a flame.</l>
               <l>Through all the ſhop of ſublunary things,</l>
               <l>Two are immortal, <hi>Phoenixes</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like Angels, each a Species makes alone,</l>
               <l>Yet neither dies without ſucceſſion.</l>
               <l>Draw, draw great Son; and let thy thirſty Steel,</l>
               <l>Their Bowels tappe till thy full Vengeance reel.</l>
               <l>Ride like a Whirle-wind driving on the floud,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Thames</hi> may know no full Sea, but of bloud.</l>
               <l>He that not follows may he drown i'th' Stream</l>
               <l>Till brave Revenge hath ſwept the Land ſo clean</l>
               <l>That all thy blaſted Enemies we ſee,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Sodomes</hi> Apples rot upon the Tree:</l>
               <l>And Travellers praiſe thy Executions,</l>
               <l>For paving Road-ways with the Rebels Bones.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THe Author of this Poem was ſometimes a Scholler in <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tons-Hoſpital;</hi> and when the Lords came to viſit, the Maſter of the School choſe this Youth to make an Oration to the Viſitors, who performed it ſo well, that my Lords Grace of <hi>Canterbury</hi> intended to prefer him; but the World growing wicked, was prevented, and he left to himſelf, (in the worſt of times) being forced to beg, till he was ſtarved, and died. He was ſo Loyal to his Prince, that he would take no Imployment from the Rebels, though it were offered him; So put pen to paper, and wrote this Elegiack Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, as a Monument in time to come of his Loyalty.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
